اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Abdullah Ibn Imam Ahmad(عَبدُالله ابن اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ), Abdullah(عَبدالله); the son of Al Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ); he said;
that he was there when his father was passing away.
And his father was going into the Sakrah(سكرة); the state of unconsciousness.
And by the way, when you are going from Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) to Akhirah(آخرة); it's a very difficult change.
You've been in this world for 60 or 70 years.
And now, you are going through a completely different world.
So that change between these two stages is difficult.
And sometimes it doesn't happen immediately.
So you'll find the person, is going back and forth in this stage of Sakrah(سكرة).
To simplify the explanation of this; think about sleep.
Because sleep is the minor death.
اَلْوَفَاةُ الصُّغْرَى
Sleep!
وٱلَّذِى يَتَوَفَّىٰكُم حینا منامکم
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And He Is the One, Who takes your souls when you are sleeping.
Sleep is a minor death.
When you are awake, and you're going to the different stage of sleep.
You go through interface between these two.
So you are not asleep, and you're not awake.
And then you enter into the stage of sleep.
So you're going from awakening to sleeping, and you're going through this interface between the two.
The same thing happens before death.
You are going through this interface between the two stages of life and death.
So there is moments in which you are on the other side of the world, and moments in which you are in this side of the world.
Abdullah Ibn Imam Ahmad(عَبدُالله ابن اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) says that, his father went into the stage of unconsciousness.
And then his father started saying;
لَا بَعَدْ، لَا بَعَدْ
No; not yet!
Abdullah(عَبدالله) was worried.
Imagine! You hear your father saying; No; not yet! No; not yet!
What would you interpret it to mean?
What would you think, it means?
I don't want to die yet, right.
No; not yet! No; not yet!
You would interpret it as meaning; I do not want to die yet.
So Abdullah(عَبدالله) was very concerned.
So he asked his father; Oh my father! When his father woke up;
Oh my father! Why were you saying; Not yet! Not yet!
Al-Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) said;
إن الشيطان قائم بحذائي عاضٌّ على أنامله
يقول: يا أحمد فتّني، يا أحمد فتّني،
فكنت أقول له: لا بعد، لا بعد، حتى أموت
Al-Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) said;
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) was standing right next to me; biting on his fingers and saying;
Oh Ahmad(اَحْمَدْ)! You have slipped out of my hands.
So I was telling him; No, not yet! Not yet! until I die.
The battle between me and you is still happening.
Not until I die; will I be saved from you.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) was biting his fingers; upset because he lost Al Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ).
Because Al Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) is slipping from his hands.
So Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) was so angry and upset.
He was biting his fingers and saying;
Ahmad(اَحْمَدْ), you have slipped away from my hands.
Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) said; Not yet; until I die.
Look at the believer! How he keeps on fighting until the last moment.
We never give up!
If we are proud; we would say, Yes! I won against you.
But Al Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) is saying; No, until I die.
So this could happen and if it could happen; is something extremely dangerous.
Imam Ibn Taymiyah(امام اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه); Shaikh-al-Islam(شيخ الاسلام), Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه); he says;
The reason, why this happens is, because Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) realizes that, this is his last chance with you.
If he misses it; you're gone.
If he misses you in the last moment, he missed you.
That is why, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) emphasizes and gives special attention to the last moments of your life.
So put the criteria to yourself and think about it; if you are losing to Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) now, when the battle is easy.
What would happen to you in the last moments, where it gets tough?
If you are already losing the battle now; when Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is giving you a half of his attention.
What will happen when he gives you his complete attention; when he devotes his efforts for you?
These are the Fitan(فِتَنْ). And that's why, we say in our Salah(صلوة);
اللهم إنا نعوذ بك من فتنة المحيا والممات
We seek refuge in You from the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of life and death.
This is the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of death.
Let's talk about Asbab Su'al Khatimah(اَسْبَابْ سُوءَالْخَاتِمَه); the reasons for evil ending.
Because the most important stage of your life is Al-Khawateem(خواتيم); the ending.
من مات على شيء بعث عليه
Whoever dies in something will be resurrected on it.
If you died in Hajj(حَجْ) with Ihram(احرام), making Talbiah(تلبيه),
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; On the Day of Judgment, you will be resurrected saying;
لَبَّيْكَ اللَّهُمَّ لَبَّيْكَ
And if you die as a Shaheed(شَهِيد) in the battle;
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; On the Day of Judgment, you would come out of your grave with your injury bleeding;
just like it was bleeding when you died in the battlefield.
من مات على شيء بعث عليه
When you die on something; you will be resurrected on that same thing that you were doing.
That's why the most important stage of our life is Al-Khawateem(الخواتیم).
And  that's why, Rasool Allah ﷺ used to always says in the Hadith(حديث);
اللهمَّ اجعل خير أعمال خواتمها
Oh Allah! Make the best of my deeds; the last deeds.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says in a Hadith(حديث);
يعمل احدكم بعمل الجنة حتى لا يكون بينها وبين الجنت ذراع،
فيسبق عليه الكتاب، فيعمل بعمل أهل النار فيدخل النار
One of you; would do the deeds of the people of paradise until, the only one foot is between you and Paradise,
and then in the end; you would do the deeds of the people of hellfire, and you would die, and you would enter into hellfire.
All of your life; you were doing the actions of the people of Jannah(جنة), and in the end; you messed up, and then you end up in hellfire.
And the opposite could happen too.
You could be doing the deeds of the people of hellfire, in the last moment of your life; you do something good; you die; you go to Jannah(جنة).
So the most important stage is the last stage.
What are the reasons for evil endings?
نسأل الله عزوجل حسن الختام
We asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; the good, blessed ending.
Reasons of evil ending.
Number one;
الفساد في الاعتقاد
Corruption and defect in the belief.
Let me give you an example, an analogy.
Let's assume; you bought a computer.
And you started working on that computer, for the first month; it's working fine, the second month it's working fine.
And then you put it through a rigorous application; and the computer failed and broke down.
You take it and you see what's the problem?
You find that there was a defect from day one.
But this defect did not show from day one, because you were treating it gently.
You were using the computer for easy and simple applications.
But when you put it through the rigorous test; a serious application; a serious program; it broke down.
Why?
Because there was a hidden defect.
This defect didn't show up on day one.
It didn't show up on day two.
It grew up fine for two months.
But when things became tough; it broke down.
Because, there was a hidden defect; You didn't see it.
You thought that the computer is brand new, and nothing is wrong with it.
But there was something hidden.
So you could be living now, thinking that your Eeman(ايمان) is perfect, and your Aqeedah(عَقِيدة) is fine.
You have a Bid'ah(بدعة) or an innovation or doubts.
You have doubts in Qur'an; doubts about the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); doubts about the laws of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
You have some doubts hidden somewhere in the corner; in the heart.
And then death approaches, and Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) puts you through the test.
Things become difficult on you in those last moments.
And that fallacy, that problem, that defect, shows up.
You find out that there was a corruption in your belief.
When you find out there's a corruption in your belief; you what do you do?
You give up your whole belief.
Because you discover there's something wrong with it; You think there's something wrong with Islam, and you would give up the whole thing,
and you would lose it all.
Just like the computer, a problem happens with it nowadays; you throw the computer; you don't go and fix it.
So you can throw the whole thing; and you lose the whole battle.
And that's why, Ibn Al-Qayyim(إبنِ ألقَيِّم) says;
We don't expect that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى would mislead anyone, who was on the straight path; except if that person had a hidden defect.
He said; We believe that, out of the Mercy of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; Allah would not mislead anyone, if that person was true righteous.
There must be something wrong, and that defect showed up in one moment of time.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قل ھل ننبِّئُكُم بِالْأَخْسَرِينَ أَعْمَالًا۝
الَّذِينَ ضَلَّ سَعْيُهُمْ فِي الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا وَهُمْ يَحْسَبُونَ أَنَّهُمْ يُحْسِنُوننَ صُنْعًا۝
Allah says; Say! Shall We tell you the greatest losers in respect to their deeds?
They are those, whom efforts have been wasted in this life, while they thought they were acquiring good by their deeds.
Allah Is telling us about the biggest losers.
They are the ones who are thinking; they're doing well; but they're doing wrong.
You find that somebody is very righteous, very righteous; but he is doing it the wrong way.
He's not following the way of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It's all unaccepted.
Second reason for Su'al Khatimah(سُوءَالْخَاتِمَه);
العدول عن الاستقامة
Diversion from the straight path.
A person could be on the straight path, and then he decides to divert.
When he takes that short cut, or short turn, what happens is; it's like a fork.
It starts out with a small angle, but then it gets further and further and further away.
The turn in the beginning seems very small; the angle is very small.
But the further you go; the more further apart you become.
Iblees(اِبْلِيس); Ar-Rajeem(الرَّجِيْم); he was one of the righteous, but he did that small mistake.
He did that small mistake out of a great problem, which is Kibr(كبر); arrogance.
And he became the worst of the creation; Bal'aam(بلعام).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَاتْلُ عَلَيْهِمْ نَبَأَ الَّذِي آتَيْنَاهُ آيَاتِنَا فَانسَلَخَ مِنْهَا
فَانسَلَخَ مِنْهَا فَأَتْبَعَهُ الشَّيْطَانُ فَكَانَ مِنَ الْغَاوِينَ۝
وَلَوْ شِئْنَا لَرَفَعْنَاهُ بِهَا وَلَٰكِنَّهُ أَخْلَدَ إِلَى الْأَرْضِ وَاتَّبَعَ هَوَاهُ ۚ
فَمَثَلُهُ كَمَثَلِ الْكَلْبِ إِن تَحْمِلْ عَلَيْهِ يَلْهَثثْ أَوْ تَتْرُكْهُ يَلْهَث ۚ
ذَّٰلِكَ مَثَلُ الْقَوْمِ الَّذِينَ كَذَّبُوا بِآيَاتِنَا ۚ فَاقْصُصِ الْقَصَصَ لَعَلَّهُمْ يَتَفَكَّرُونَ۝
Allah says; And recite to them the story of him, to whom We gave our Ayaat(آيات), but he threw them away.
So Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) followed him up, and he became of those who went astray, and hell We built, We would surely Have elevated him therewith,
but he clung to the earth and followed his own vain desires.
This Ayah(آية) is talking about someone who received the Ayaat(آيات) of Allah,
received the Ayaat(آيات) of Allah,
and then he detached himself from the Ayaat(آيات) of Allah, and followed his own desires.
So Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) followed up, and he was misled and misguided.
Why?
أَخْلَدَ إِلَى الْأَرْضِ
Because he was clung and attached to this world.
Look at what this world could do.
This is a person who had the knowledge and had the Ayaat(آيات) of Allah; he lost it all and was misguided.
Why?
Because of his attachment to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), and why?
وَاتَّبَعَ هَوَاهُ ۚ
Because he followed his own desires.
Do not follow desires and do not follow this world.
Because that is contrary to the meaning of the word Islam.
Let's go back to the basics; Islam; what does it mean?
Submission to Allah.
You submit to Allah even if it's against to your own will; even if it's against your own desires.
You give up what you want, for the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
We want to follow the religion according to our understandings, and according to our convenience, and to our spare time.
No! We do not custom make Islam to serve us.
We change ourselves to fit in Islam.
We do not make Islam change; we change our own characters to fit Islam.
Because this is the meaning of the world Islam; it is complete submission; submission to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
This man; he had the knowledge, and he had the Ayaat(آيات) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, he didn't do him, any good.
Because he was followed his own desires and he was mislead.
قَال صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ:إِنَّ مِمَّا أَتَخَوَّفُ عَلَيْكُمْ رَجُلٌ قَرَأَ الْقُرْآنَ حَتَّى إِذَا رُئِيَتْ بَهْجَتُهُ  عَلَى وَجْهِه
وَعَلَيْهِ رِدْءًا لِلإِسْلامِ اِعْتَرَاهُ إِلَى مَا شَاءَ اللَّهُ،
انْسَلَخَ مِنْهُ , وَنَبَذَهُ وَرَاءَ ظَهْرِهِ , وَخَرَجَ عَلَى جَارِهِ بِالسَّيْفِ وَرَمَاهُ بِالشِّرْكِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
The thing that I fear most on you; is a man who memorizes Qur'an; until the light of Qur'an shows up on his face,
and then he detaches himself from the Ayaat(آيات) of Allah,
and he carries the sword on his neighbour, and he accuses him of Shirk(شرك).
He accuses him, that he's a Mushrik(مشرك); a nonbeliever.
Hadifah bil Yaman(حديفه باليمان) said;
يا رسول الله، أيهما أولى بالشرك، المرمي أم الرامي؟
فقَال صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ: بل الرامي
Hadifah bil Yaman(حديفه باليمان) asked Rasool Allah ﷺ;
Who is the Mushrik(مشرك) among them.
The accuser or the accused.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; The accuser.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says that this is; Asna'd Jaiyid(اسناد جید).
This is a man who has Qur'an in his heart, and Qur'an is showing from his face; the light of Qur'an.
But then, he detached himself from Qur'an.
He fell into the Fitnah(فِتْنَه); a Fitnah(فِتْنَه); and he carried the sword on his neighbour; a Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
And he accuses his neighbour of Shirk(شرك).
So Rasool Allah ﷺ says that, this man; he has became a Mushrik(مشرك).
Qur'an is still in his heart; he became a Mushrik(مشرك).
In another story, and we'll close with this.
Barseesah(برسيسه); the story of Barseesah(برسيسه); this is a man from the children of Israel(اسرائيل),
who was a worshipper; famous worshipper; Abid(عابد).
He had his temple, and he devoted himself to worship in his monastery.
Three men from the children of Israel(اسرائيل) wanted to go out for Jihad(جهاد); Al-Ghazwoo(الغزو).
They had a sister.
They didn't know where to leave their sister.
So they said; Where should we leave her, we can't leave her alone?
Where should we leave her?
They asked around;
they said the best place to leave her is with that Abid(عابد); that worshiper.
He is the most righteous person; he is the most trustworthy; leave your sister with him; and he will take care of her.
They went to the Abid(عابد); the worshipper; Barseesah(برسيسه).
They told him; this is a situation; we want to go out for Ghazu(غزو), can you please take care of our sister?
He said;
اَعُوْذُ بِالله مِنْكُمْ
I seek refuge in Allah from you! Stay away from me.
Then Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to him and said;
Who are you going to leave her with?
If you don't take care of her, an evil person may take care of her and then you know what will happen.
How come you going to leave this good slip out of your hands.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is encouraging him to do good.
So he called them back and said; Okay, I'll take care of her.
She's not going to stay with me in my monastery; she's going to stay in that home over there.
He had a house, he said; You stay there; I stay in my temple.
So she would stay in that house, in the room.
And he would carry the food for her and he would leave the food on his doorstep; he doesn't even want to go to her house.
He would leave it on the doorstep and she would have to come and pick up the food; He does not even want to see her.
And then, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to him and said; What are you doing?
Don't you know that when she walks out from her room and comes to your temple; people can see her.
You have to deliver the food to her doorstep.
He said, yes; that's true.
And Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is not speaking to him face to face, this is waswasa(وسوسه); inspirations.
He said, that's true.
He started taking that food, and he would drop it on her doorstep.
That continue for a while, and then Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) told him;
She's still opening the door and coming out to take the plate, somebody can still see her.
You have to deliver the plate into her own room.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is telling him to do good things.
So he started taking the plate, and he would put it in the room, and then he would leave.
And that continued for a while, and these three brother were late.
This Ghazwa(غزوة) took a while.
So Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to him and said;
You are going to leave her alone, with nobody to take care of her; nobody to speak with;
she is been in there like, she is in prison; speaking to no one.
So why don't you take that responsibility, and go and speak with her, and just socialize a little bit to take care of her.
Because she could go out, and find another man, and start having a relation with him.
So he would speak from outside her room, and she would be speaking from in her room,
and they would be screaming at each other to hear each other.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) told him; Why don't you make it a little bit convenient for yourself?
Instead of screaming and hollering at each other from far distances; why don't you go and sit in the same room?
So he started sitting with her in the same room, spending some time with her,
and then slowly and slowly, they started spending hours together.
And they started getting closer and closer and closer until, the great Abid(عابد) committed Zina(زنا).
She became pregnant.
The story didn't end yet.
She delivered a child.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to him and said; What have you done?
Do you know what will happen when the brothers come back?
They're going to kill you.
And even if you say, this is not my son;
they're going to say, Even if it's not your son, you're supposed to take care of her; it's your responsibility.
We don't care, who the father is.
We left her to you, You are the person responsible for her.
The only solution for this problem is that you kill; murder the child, and bury him.
Secret after he killed her son.
Do you think she will keep that secret?
You're a fool; if you think so.
What should I do?
You should kill her too.
So he killed her, and he buried them both in that room.
The brothers came back.
They came and said; Where is our sister?
He said;
إِنَّا لِلَّهِ وَإِنَّا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعُونَ۝
She became ill, and she died, and she is buried in that place.
And he went and showed them a fictitious grave.
So they said;
إِنَّا لِلَّهِ وَإِنَّا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعُونَ۝
They made Dua(دُعَا) for her, and they went home.
At night time, one of the brothers saw a dream.
Who came to him in that dream?
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
He told them; Did you believe Barseesah(برسيسه); did you believe him?
He's lying.
He committed Zina(زنا) with your sister, and then he killed her and her son.
And the evidence to prove that is that; she's not buried in the place he showed you; but she's buried in her room under the rock.
So he woke up, and he told his brothers about the dream.
They said; We saw the same dream.
It must be true.
They went the next day; they dug the fictitious grave; they found nothing.
They went into her room; they uncovered the earth; and they found their sister buried with an infant.
They grabbed Barseesah(برسيسه), and they told him; You're a liar.
This is what you have done and they took him to the king.
While they were dragging him to the king; Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to Barseesah(برسيسه).
But now Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), didn't come in the form of inspiration.
He came in a human form.
He told him; Barseesah(برسيسه)! Do you know who I am?
I am Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ)! I am the one who caused you all of that mess,
and I am the only one who can deliver you out of it.
I am the one who caused it, and I am the one who has the solution for it.
It's up to you; if you want to go and die; that's fine.
If you wants me to save you; I can.
Barseesah(برسيسه) said; Please save me.
He said; Make Sujood(سجود) for me.
Barseesah(برسيسه) make Sujood(سجود) for Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
What did Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) say?
He said; Thank you very much! It was a pleasure meeting you; and he never saw him again.
Barseesah(برسيسه) made Sujood(سجود) for Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
And that was the last thing he did in his life because shortly afterwards, he was executed.
The last thing he did in his life was Sujood(سجود) for Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
Abid(عابد) on the righteous path.
But because he chose to take a turn; even though it was a very, very, very small turn.
In the beginning, it was very insignificant in the name of Muslahah(مصلحة); in the name of the benefit.
In the name of Muslahah(مصلحة), he did it.
And it was a very small diversion that he took.
But look at, where it ended; look at the final destination.
That is the danger of following desire.
Because sometimes we feel confident because of our knowledge, and because of the Qur'an we know,
and because of the Ibadah(عبادة) that we're doing.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)! We should always be afraid on ourselves.
We should never be overconfident.
We should always be worried and that is the Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and that is the true knowledge.
إِنَّمَا يَخْشَى اللَّهَ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ الْعُلَمَاءُ
The ones who have the Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allah; the fear of Allah; are the scholars.
If you are scholar then you have Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allah
otherwise, it is just memorization of verses in the mind that has no meaning in the actual world.
A side note on this story; What policy was Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) using with Barseesah(برسيسه)?
If Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) came to Barseesah(برسيسه) from the beginning and told him, make Sujood(سجود) to me;
would Barseesah(برسيسه) have done that?
No he wouldn't.
He took the step by step policy.
Ibn Josie(ابن جوزى) says that, there was a man named, Abdul Ibn Abdul-Raheem(عبدل ابن عبدالرّحيم).
This was in year 280 or 270 Hijri.
Abdul Ibn Abdul-Raheem(عبدل ابن عبدالرّحيم); he was a Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) with the Muslim armies that were fighting in the Roman Empire.
And he fought in Jihad(جهاد) for a long time.
And on one of their battles; actually, they were surrounding a Roman fortress.
They were surrounding them and while they were surrounding them; this man saw a woman.
فَفْتُتِنَا بِهَا
It was a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for him.
So he started corresponding with this woman.
This woman is a Roman woman in that city, the Muslims are surrounding them.
What he did is, he started corresponding with her.
And he asked her; How can I get in?
So she told him; Become a Christian, and I'll let you in.
So he became a Christian.
And the next day, suddenly the Muslim saw this man; this Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), he was with them; he's inside with the Romans.
This thing depressed them a lot.
Because this man has fought in Jihad(جهاد) for very long time, and he knew a lot of Qur'an, and he had a lot of knowledge.
And suddenly, now here, he gave up his religion, and he became a Christian to run after that woman.
Ten years passed, and some Muslims who knew that man, they passed next to that Roman village or Fort again.
So they saw him.
And they told him; come with us.
He said; No, I cannot come with you, that's it; I'm settled here.
I'm married, and I have children, and I have business.
I'm already settled here.
He gave up his religion; He was a Christian now, hanging the cross.
So they told him; Where did your Jihad(جهاد) go?
What happened to your Jihad(جهاد)?
What happened to your knowledge; What happened to your Qur'an?
He said; Oh! I forgot all of that.
I forgot all of Qur'an except one verse.
رُّبَمَا يَوَدُّ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لَوْ كَانُوا مُسْلِمِينَ۝
ذَرْهُمْ يَأْكُلُوا وَيَتَمَتَّعُوا وَيُلْهِهِمُ الْأَمَلُ ۖ فَسَوْففَ يَعْلَمُونَ۝
He said; I have forgot all of Qur'an except one verse, where Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
One day the non believers will desire that they were believers.
So let them eat and enjoy themselves, and let them follow the false hopes and desires; but soon they will know.
He forgot all the Qur'an except this.
He remembers a verse that is telling him that, one day the non believers will desire and wish that they were Muslim.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ذَرْهُمْ يَأْكُلُوا وَيَتَمَتَّعُوا
Let them eat and let them enjoy themselves.
فَسَوْفَ يَعْلَمُونَ۝
One day, they will know.
وَيُلْهِهِمُ الْأَمَلُ ۖ
Let the false desires fool them.
But one day, they will realize the truth.
When you diverge; when you diverge from the straight path, this is what happens.
This man; he was a Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), and he knew Qur'an, and he memorized a lot of Ayaat(آيات),
and he has a lot of knowledge; but he didn't stick to the straight path.
فَاسْتَقِمْ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tells Rasool Allah ﷺ;
After you received the guidance; follow the straight path.
And one of the companions came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him; Give me an advice.
Oh Rasool Allah ﷺ! Give me the best advice.
Give me an advice that I would not have to ask anybody else for another advice.
I want you to give me one advice that will be sufficient for me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُلْ آمَنْتُ بِاللهِ، ثُمَّ اسْتَقِمْ
Say; I believe in Allah, and then stay on the straight path.
Because we can say, we believe; we can say that, we're Muslims, but the important thing is to stay on the straight path.
That's where the test is, and that's where a lot of people fail.
They followed the truth for a while; but then the winds of change in this world take them from right to left.
And this is the ending that happened to him.
Why?
He missed As-Sabat(اثّبات); As-Sabat al-Haqq(اثّبات الحَقّ); staying on the straight path.
You slip and you don't know how deep that cliff is.
That is the Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; you know the truth, and you are so worried,
that you're asking Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in Salah(صلوة) 17 times; in Salah(صلوۃ)
إِيَّاكَ نَعْبُدُ وَإِيَّاكَ نَسْتَعِينُ۝ ٱهْدِنَا ٱلصِّرَاطَ ٱلْمُسْتَقِيمَ۝
Oh Allah! We seek assistance from You, and we worship nobody except You; so guide us to the straight path.
We keep on asking Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in the fareeza(فريضه) seventeen, times, to keep us on the straight path.
And then in the Nawafil(نَوَافِلْ) we read Al-Fatihah(اَلْفَاتِحه),
why are we repeating this Ayah(آية) again and again;
ٱهْدِنَا ٱلصِّرَاطَ ٱلْمُسْتَقِيمَ۝
Because, it's very important to stay on the straight path.
The third reason of evil ending; evil conclusion of one's life; Su'al Khatimah(سُوءَالْخَاتِمَه) is;
الإصرار على المعاصي
Insistence on sining.
A person might be committing a small sin,
but the Ulama(عُلَمَا) say; that insisting on a small sin makes it a major sin.
When you keep on doing it again and again; it becomes a major sin.
And Adh-Dhahabi(الذهبى); in his book, Al-Kabair(الكبائر); he talks about some of the evil endings.
He said; There was a man who used to be obsessed with chess.
When he was dying; They told him, say;
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
He couldn't say it.
And then, just before he died; he kept on repeating checkmate, checkmate, checkmate, until he died.
Because he was thinking about chess.
Adh-Dhahabi(الذهبى) mentions another man; they came and told him; say;
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
He said; Give me the bottle, give me a cup; I want to drink; Khamr(خمر) alcohol!
Because he was addicted to alcohol; That is the thought that came on his mind in the last moment.
Ar-Rabi'ah bin Saburah(الرّبيعه بن صبوره); he says that,
he witnessed the death of a man, who used to work in Ad-Deewan(الدّيوان); an accountant; he's always calculating numbers.
And before he died; they were telling him; say,
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
He would say; 10, 11, 12, and he was counting numbers until he died.
Ibn Al-Qayyim(إبنِ ألقَيِّم) mentions a story of someone who was dying; they told him say;
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
He said; I can't!
He didn't have a problem with his tongue; he could speak fluently, but he could not say;
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
Allah did not give him the Tawfeeq(توفيق); Allah did not allow him to say it.
Because, he did not have a life record of,
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
Think about it, this way.
Think about Sakrat-ul-Maut(سَكْرَاةُالْمَوت) in this way.
When you go to bed; what are the things you dream about?
Most likely, they're going to be things, you are thinking about consistently during the day.
When you keep on thinking about something; there's a big chance that you could see that thing or dream about it at night.
Also another way to know what's on your mind, is when you wake up in the morning.
As soon as you wake up; what is the first thought that pops up in your mind?
Because death is similar to sleep.
اَلْوَفَاةُ الصُّغْرَى
Sleeping is called;
The minor death.
So when you're going from sleep to the state of awakening; it is similar to that stage of Sakrat-ul-Maut(سَكْرَاةُالْمَوت).
So that's why, the thoughts that are on one's mind are most likely going to show up in the last moments of one's life.
We always think about it that; I'm going to do whatever I want, I'm going to sin the way I like,
and then before I die; five minutes before I die; I'm going to say;
لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ
And I'm guaranteed Jannah(جنة).
It's not that easy.
وَيَمْكُرُونَ وَيَمْكُرُ اللَّهُ ۖ
You are making a plan; you are plotting against Allah.
This is a plot against Allah.
When you say this; you are plotting against Allah.
Why?
Because you're telling Allah; I'm not going to worship You.
You are making the intention that you're not going to worship Allah, until the last moment of your life.
What is that?
Isn't that planning against Allah.
I'm going to do what I want now when I'm young; and then I'm going to think about Tawbah(توبة) when I grow old.
You are planning against Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allah is telling you worship me every day and night in your life.
You say; No!
I'm going to try to go around this rule, and sneak around it, and then make Tawbah(توبة) in the end.
I'm going to outsmart Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
وَيَمْكُرُونَ وَيَمْكُرُ اللَّهُ ۖ وَاللَّهُ خَيْرُ الْمَاكِرِينَ۝
They are plotting in Allah's planning; and Allah Is The Best of Planners.
There's one scholar; just a few weeks ago, he mentioned to us a factual story that happened.
They were visiting an old man who was dying.
They came in the house, and when they came in the household;
all of the household; they were listening to loud, Umme Kulthum(امّ كلثوم) music.
Umme Kulthum(امّ كلثوم) is an Arabic singer.
The man was in the last moments of his life; and the tape recorder was to the highest volume; listening to the songs of Umme Kulthum(امّ كلثوم).
This Shaikh(شيخ) came in and told them;
اتَّقُوا اللَّهَ
Fear Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; the man is dying, and you're listening to songs.
So they took out that tape, and they put Qur'an instead.
When the old man started hearing Qur'an, he said; turn it off and put Umme Kulthum(امّ كلثوم) back;
because she soothes my heart, and he died.
مَنْ شَبَّ على شَيْءٍ شَابَّ عَلَيْه
When you grow up on something, you're going to die on that thing.
If you grow up doing something most likely, the conclusion of your life will be on that thing you were doing.
Never think that you can outsmart Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
You have to have Khash'ya(خَشْية) of Allah.
The ones who are safe; feel safe and secure of the punishment of Allah are the losers.
لَا يَأْمَنُ مَكْرَ ٱللَّهِ إِلَّا ٱلْقَوْمُ ٱلْخَٰسِرُونَ۝
Only, the losers are the ones who feel secure from the punishment of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Khash'ya(خَشْية) is an integral quality of the Muslim.
To be a Mo'min(مؤمن) and a believer; you have to have Khash'ya(خَشْية); fear of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in your heart.
The fourth reason of evil endings is; Za'aful Eeman(ضعف الايمان); weak faith; weak Eeman(ايمان).
Sulayman Ibn Abdul Malik(سليمان ابن عبدالملك); Al-Khalifah Al-Amvi(الخليفة الأموي); the Khalifah of the Muslim world.
He visited Makkah(مكه) and Madinah(مَدِينَه).
So he was asking; Is there anyone here, who has met the companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ?
They said; Yes, Abu Hazim(ابو حازم).
He said; Call him.
So they brought Abu Hazim(ابو حازم).
Sulayman Ibn Abdul Malik(سليمان ابن عبدالملك) asked him a question.
He said; How come we dislike death?
How come we don't want to die?
He said;
لإنكم عمرتم الدنيا وخربتم الآخرة،
فتكرهون الخروج من العمران إلى الخراب
He said; Because you have built and established this world, and you have destroyed your Akhirah(آخرة),
so you hate to go from what is established to what is destroyed.
You have built for yourself a good life in this world.
You have established for yourself a good, pleasurable, pleasant life in this world.
And you have destroyed your hereafter.
You didn't do anything for it; You left it; Destroyed.
You didn't build anything.
So you don't want to go from what you have established to what you have destroyed.
Natural consequence.
If you're not preparing for Akhirah(آخرة), why would you want to go there?
This is due to Za'aful Eeman(ضعف الايمان) and what is the cause of Za'aful Eeman(ضعف الايمان)?
It is the love of this world; the love of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
When we love this world; we do not want to go to Akhirah(آخرة).
And the love of this world could cause a very, very destructive and dangerous thing in the end of your life.
The scholars have said; If somebody has the love of this world in his heart;
then just before that person's death;
when the person starts realizing that he's going to leave the lovable Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and go to Akhirah(آخرة);
the person would become attached to the thing he loves.
He would become attached to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), and then that person could start hating Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
because Allah Is The One Who wants to take him away from Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
The Ulema(علماء) say, that can happen to the person in the end of his life.
And they say, if that happens; this is Khulud Fin-Nar(خُلُود فِالنَّار).
This is a eternal punishment in hellfire.
Because you are hating to meet Allah; you dislike meeting Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, so Allah will dislike meeting you.
Muadh Ibn Jabal(معاذاِبن جبل); when he was passing away,
he said; Welcome to death! I've been waiting for you for a long time.
I've been waiting for the Promise of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to me.
Welcome to death! He's happy.
And then he said; Oh Death! Don't think that I ever wanted to live in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), because of the love of this world.
The reason why I wanted to live in this world; is to fast in the hot summer days,
and to pray at night in the long cold winter nights.
So as long as now it's time for me to leave; I welcome you.
Take my soul.
He wants to meet Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; so Allah would want to meet him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Al Bukhari(البخاريْ);
إنه لم يقبض نبي قط حتى يرى مقعده من الجنة ثم يخير
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Bukhari(بخاريْ);
Every prophet, before he dies is shown his place in Paradise, and then he's given the choice to stay in this world or to die.
So the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are given the choice.
This Hadith(حديث) is narrated by Ayesha(عائشه).
She says; Rasool Allah ﷺ has said that every prophet before he passes away; he is shown his place in Paradise,
and then he is given the choice to die or to live.
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ was dying; he had his head on my lap.
And then he fell unconscious, and then he woke up, and he started staring at the sky,
and then he said;
اللَّهُمَّ رَفيقِ الأعلَى
Oh Allah! The highest companion, Oh Allah! The highest companion.
Meaning I want to be with the highest companion, which is who?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Ayesha(عائشه) said; I knew that Rasool Allah ﷺ that moment, was being given the choice, and that he was not choosing us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying;
اللَّهُمَّ رَفيقِ الأعلَى
Oh Allah! the highest companion.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ was given the offer by the angel of death;
he was asking him; Do you want to stay, or do you want to leave?
Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying; I want to be with Allah.
Ayesha(عائشه) said; I knew that he's not choosing us.
And that was the last word Rasool Allah ﷺ said.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تسلیما کثیرا